Iegor Riepin

I am a postdoctoral researcher at the <u>Energy Systems</u> group @ TU Berlin.

My research focuses on energy economics, operations research, and energy-related programmable matter. The overarching goal is to find cost-effective opportunities for climate neutrality.

I find it enjoyable to answer challenging questions using mathematical models. I believe in open science, and I try to contribute by sharing my code, data and teaching materials.



Personal page: <u>iriepin.com/</u>

LinkedIn: <u>linkedin.com/in/iegor-riepin/</u>

E: <u>iegor.riepin@tu-berlin.de</u> | <u>iegor.riepin@gmail.com</u>

Work experience

2022.03 – Postdoctoral researcher | Energy system modeler

present Department of Energy Systems <u>ENSYS @ TU Berlin</u>

I spend most of my time writing and solving mathematical models in the energy field. Our group maintains the PyPSA ecosystem - an open-source python environment for state-of-the-art energy system modelling: https://pypsa.org/

Currently I work on the <u>24/7 Carbon-Free Energy by 2030</u> project by Google. In October 2022, we published a <u>study</u> on the system-level impacts of 24/7 CFE procurement. In July 2023, we published a <u>study</u> on the value of space-time load-shifting flexibility for data centers. The research work on this project is open and reproducible: https://github.com/PyPSA/247-cfe

2014.11 - Research fellow | PhD student

2022.02 ESM group lead (2021.09 – 2022.02)

Brandenburg University of Technology (BTU CS), Germany

Chair of Energy Economics

I have carried out independent and third-party funded research in the fields of energy economics and energy systems modeling. The topics included infrastructure investments, decisions under uncertainty, risk-aversion, sector coupling and energy auctions.

2019.09 – Visiting researcher

2019.10 University of Victoria, Canada | <u>Institute for Integrated Energy Systems</u>

My work was focused on robust optimization algorithms applied to

electricity system expansion problems.

2013.10	_	Student assistant
2014.09		Chair of Energy Economics, BTU CS
2013.09		Intern
2013.10		DIW Berlin, Institute for Economic Research, Germany
		Department: Energy, Transportation, Environment

Academic background

2014.11 -	PhD (summa cum laude) in energy economics
2022.06	Supervision: Prof. Felix Müsgens BTU CS
	PhD thesis 'Modeling challenges of modern energy markets: studies on uncertainty, complexity, and constant change' is <u>published in open access</u> .
2012 - 2014	M.Sc. (Hon) in Power Engineering BTU CS, Germany Final grade: 1.2 (/1)
2008 - 2012	B.Sc. (Hon) in Heat Power Engineering ZSEA, Ukraine Final grade: 4.98 (/5)

Third-party projects

2022.03 -	@TUB: 24/7 Carbon-Free Energy Procurement. Funding: Google
present	LLC. See Operating on 24/7 Carbon Free Energy by 2030 webpage.
2021	@BTU: TransHyDE: System analysis of transport solutions for green
(ongoing)	hydrogen. Funding: BMBF (Federal Ministry of Education and Research)
	Cooperation: >30 partners Project web page
2017	@BTU: Design of auctions for market premia for onshore wind generation: theoretical and experimental testing. Cooperation: CERGE-EI. Summary
2016	@BTU: Strategy 2020: modelling of forward prices for natural gas
	in European gas markets. Funding: industry partner. Cooperation: <u>r2b</u> energy consulting GmbH
2014 - 2016	@BTU: Fundamental gas market analysis in a context of the
	German energy transition process. Funding: gas trading utility.
	Cooperation: <u>r2b energy consulting GmbH</u> . <u>Summary</u>

Peer-reviewed journal articles

1. Energy Economics (2023). Risk aversion and flexibility options in electricity markets

Möbius, T., Riepin, I., Müsgens, F., van der Weijde A. H. DOI: doi.org/10.1016/j.eneco.2023.106767
Working paper at arXiv (2021) | Code

2. Working paper. Temporal regulation of renewable supply for electrolytic hydrogen

Zeyen, E., Riepin, I., Brown, T.

Working paper DOI: https://zenodo.org/records/8324521 | Code

3. Applied Energy (2022). Adaptive robust optimization for European strategic gas infrastructure planning

Riepin, I., Schmidt, M., Baringo, L., Müsgens, F.,

DOI: <u>doi.org/10.1016/j.apenergy.2022.119686</u> | <u>Code</u>

Working paper at Optimization Online (2021)

4. Energy Policy (2022). Policy choices and outcomes for the global competitive procurement of offshore wind

Jansen, M., Beiter, P., Riepin, I., Müsgens, F. Juarez Guajardo-Fajardo, V., Staffell, I., Bulder, B., Kitzing, L.

DOI: 10.1016/j.enpol.2022.113000 | Data

Working paper at arXiv (2022)

5. Applied Energy (2021). Modelling uncertainty in coupled electricity and gas systems—Is it worth the effort?

Riepin, I., Möbius, T., Müsgens, F.

DOI: 10.1016/j.apenergy.2020.116363 | Code

Working paper at arXiv (2020): arxiv.org/abs/2008.07221

6. Nature Energy (2020). Offshore wind competitiveness in mature markets without subsidy.

Jansen, M., Staffell, I., Kitzing, L., Quoilin, S., Wiggelinkhuizen, E., Bulder, B., Riepin, I., Müsgens, F.

DOI: <u>10.1038/s41560-020-0661-2</u> | <u>Code</u> | <u>Supplementary data</u>

Nature Energy News & Views | Media coverage: 118 news stories from 116 outlets

7. The Energy Journal (2022). Seasonal flexibility in the European natural gas market.

Riepin, I., Müsgens, F.

DOI: 10.5547/01956574.43.1.irie | Code

Cambridge Working Papers in Economics (2019)

DOI: 10.17863/CAM.43923 | Abstract | Non-Technical Summary | PDF

(Mostly peer-reviewed) Conference papers

8. IEEE EEM (2022). Modeling of Extreme Weather Events—Towards Resilient Transmission Expansion Planning.

Bernecker, M., Riepin, I., Müsgens, F.

DOI: <u>10.1109/EEM54602.2022.9921145</u>

9. IEEE EEM (2020). Regret analysis of investment decisions under uncertainty in an integrated energy system.

Möbius, T., Riepin, I.

DOI: 10.1109/EEM49802.2020.9221935

10. IEEE EEM (2018). Integrated electricity and gas market modeling – effects of gas demand uncertainty.

Riepin, I., Möbius, T., Müsgens, F.

DOI: <u>10.1109/EEM.2018.8469790</u> | <u>preprint version</u> | <u>Video</u>

11. IEEE EEM (2018). Is offshore already competitive? Analyzing German offshore wind auctions.

Müsgens, F., Riepin, I.

DOI: <u>10.1109/EEM.2018.8469851</u> | <u>preprint version</u> | <u>Video</u>

12. IEEE EEM (2016). Modelling of world LNG market development: focus on US investments and supplies.

Montenegro, R., Riepin, I., Hauser, P.

DOI: <u>10.1109/EEM.2016.7521361</u>

13. ZSEA (2011). Usage of solar energy for heating service and domestic water heating.

Riepin, I. | VII all-Ukrainian scientific conference. Vol. 2, pp. 78 - 83.

14. ZSEA (2011). Ukrainian market prospects in the field of alternative energy sources.

Riepin, I. | The annual conference for graduate students. pp. 186 - 192.

Science explainers, media, project reports

15. Environment Variables podcast (November 2023): The Week in Green Software: Modeling Carbon Aware Software.

Podcast link

16. Project study (2023). The value of space-time load-shifting flexibility for 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement

Riepin, I. and Brown, T.

Zenodo

17. Project study (2022). System-level impacts of 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement in Europe.

Riepin, I. and Brown, T.

Zenodo

18. SSRN (2021). Grok it and use it: Teaching energy systems modeling

Riepin, I., Sgarciu, S., Bernecker, M., Möbius, T., Müsgens, F.

DOI: dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4320978 | Course GitHub

19. CarbonBrief (2020). The era of 'negative-subsidy' offshore wind power has almost arrived

Riepin, I., Jansen, M., Staffell, I., Müsgens, F.

Guest post

20. e|m|w.trends (2020). Offshore-Windenergie - subventionsfrei?

Müsgens, F. and Riepin, I.

Guest post

21. Oxford Institute for Energy Studies & BTU CS (2015). A note on climate policy negotiations at the threshold of COP-21 in Paris.

Müsgens, F., Poudineh, R., Riepin, I. PDF

Some public talks

1. On space-time load-shifting flexibility for 24/7 carbon-free electricity procurement

PDF @ Eurelectric 24/7 Carbon Free Energy (CFE) Hub meeting, October 2023

2. Technical Research Fueling NextGen Actions

Youtube @ Linux Foundation Energy summit, panel discussion, Paris

3. Navigating to a greener Europe with 24/7 hourly clean electricity procurement

PDF | Code @ Enerday, Dresden 2023

4. 24/7 A new paradigm for power procurement?

PDF | Code @ European Climate and Energy Modelling Platform 2022

5. European Natural Gas Infrastructure Expansion Planning: An Adaptive Robust Optimization Approach

PDF | Code @ EWI Cologne & BTU CS Research seminars 2021

PDF | Code @ European Conference on Operational Research, Athens, 2021

6. The costs of ignoring uncertainty and the value of perfect information: a toy model.

PDF | Code @ Doctoral seminar, BTU CS, 2019

7. Robust optimization of electricity system expansion.

PDF | Code @ University of Victoria, Canada, 2019

8. Economic impacts of uncertainty in integrated electricity and gas markets.

PDF @ 30th European Conference on Operational Research, Dublin, Ireland, 2019

9. Integrated electricity and gas market modelling – effects of gas demand uncertainty.

PDF @ EEM2018 Conference, Lodz, Poland, 2018

PDF @ PhD seminar Cottbus-Leipzig-Dresden, 2018

10. Integration of electricity and gas market models.

PDF @ Energy modelling seminar, IER, Universität Stuttgart, 2018

11. Application of non-linear and complementarity problems for natural gas market modelling.

PDF @ Research seminar with chair of Mathematical Economics, BTU CS, 2017

PDF @ Internal research seminar, BTU CS, 2016

12. Natural Gas Storages in Competition with Alternative Flexibility Sources.

PDF @ 39th IAEE International Conference, Bergen, Norway, 2016

PDF @ PhD seminar Cottbus-Leipzig-Dresden, 2016

13. Prospects for Shale Gas Exploration in Europe: Ongoing Experience.

PDF @ 38th IAEE International Conference, Antalya, Turkey, 2015

Teaching experience

2014 - present	Supervision of master's and bachelor's theses, and study projects in energy economics and all around modeling of energy systems.
WS17/18 WS18/19 WS19/20	Energy Systems Modeling (course development, selected lectures, tutorials, supervision of student projects) Lecture: Prof. Dr. Felix Müsgens <u>Course GitHub page</u>
From WS14/15 until SS2018	Power System Economics 1 (Winter terms tutorials) Power System Economics 2 (Summer terms tutorials) Lecture: Prof. Dr. Felix Müsgens and Prof. Dr. Stefan Zundel

Scholarships & awards

2017 - 2019	Postgraduate scholarship, BTU CS (Promotionsstipendium des Landes Brandenburg, $\operatorname{GradV})$
2014	Rheinstahl foundation study scholarship (Master degree)
2013	STIBET study scholarship, DAAD (Master degree)
2010	Zaporizhia city administration scholarship (Bachelor degree)

Some technical skills and languages

Mathematical	GAMS (project-related use, research and teaching)
modeling &	Python (project-related use, research and hobby projects)
programming	Git (version control)
	Snakemake (scientific workflow management)
Languages	English (fluent) German (C1 certificate)
	Ukrainian (native fluent) Russian (native fluent)

Follow the stars

https://iriepin.com/post/

Berlin, November 2023